<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<!-- *ActualQuotes* by Willowmound, ver. 4.20 (Beyond the Sword) -->
<!-- Leader-specific diplomacy text based on actual quotes, complete or paraphrased. Some other minor changes. -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LINCOLN_1</Tag>
		<English>Ah, [CT_NAME]. I am honoured. I've always said, the best way to destroy an enemy is to make him a friend. What do you say -- friends?</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! Je suis [OUR_NAME]. C'est un honneur de vous rencontrer.</French>
		<German>Seid gegrüßt, [CT_NAME]. Mein Name ist [OUR_NAME]. Es ist mir eine Ehre, Eure Bekanntschaft zu machen.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]. Sono [OUR_NAME]. È davvero un onore incontrarti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Soy [OUR_NAME]. Es todo un honor conoceros.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LINCOLN_2</Tag>
		<English>Come in. I am [OUR_NAME], leader of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Don't worry when you are not recognized. But do strive to be worthy of recognition. Will you sign a treaty of peace?</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! Je suis [OUR_NAME]. C'est un honneur de vous rencontrer.</French>
		<German>Seid gegrüßt, [CT_NAME]. Mein Name ist [OUR_NAME]. Es ist mir eine Ehre, Eure Bekanntschaft zu machen.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]. Sono [OUR_NAME]. È davvero un onore incontrarti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Soy [OUR_NAME]. Es todo un honor conoceros.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_LINCOLN_1</Tag>
		<English>What kills a skunk is the publicity it gives itself.</English>
		<French>Allez vous faire voir !</French>
		<German>Fahrt zur Hölle!</German>
		<Italian>Sparisci.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Podéis iros al cuerno.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_LINCOLN_1</Tag>
		<English>Those who deny freedom to others deserve it not for themselves.</English>
		<French>Comme un ami m'a dit un jour, "Aucune condition ne saurait être acceptée, hormis une capitulation immédiate et inconditionnelle." Dommage, n'est-ce pas ?</French>
		<German>Wie ein Freund von mir zu sagen pflegte: 'Ich akzeptiere nur die sofortige und bedingungslose Kapitulation'. Äußerst treffend, nicht wahr?</German>
		<Italian>Come disse una volta un mio amico: &quot;L'unica cosa accettabile è una resa incondizionata e immediata.&quot; Conciso, non trovi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Como un amigo mío dijo una vez: &quot;Ninguna condición es aceptable, salvo una rendición incondicional e inmediata&quot;. Es una lástima, ¿no creéis?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_LINCOLN_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME], old friend. I like to see a man proud of the place in which he lives. I like to see a man live so that his place will be proud of him. In short, I like you, [CT_NAME]. Drink?</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! Asseyez-vous et bavardons un instant.</French>
		<German>Seid gegrüßt, [CT_NAME]. Nehmt Platz und lasst uns ein wenig plaudern.</German>
		<Italian>Salve, [CT_NAME]. Siediti e parliamo per un po'.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Sentaos y charlemos un rato.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_LINCOLN_2</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME]! Come in. It has been my experience that folks who have no vices have very few virtues. You, my dear friend, sure have both.</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! Asseyez-vous et bavardons un instant.</French>
		<German>Seid gegrüßt, [CT_NAME]. Nehmt Platz und lasst uns ein wenig plaudern.</German>
		<Italian>Salve, [CT_NAME]. Siediti e parliamo per un po'.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Sentaos y charlemos un rato.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_LINCOLN_1</Tag>
		<English>If I had eight hours to chop down a tree, I'd spend six sharpening my axe. I'm sharpening, [CT_NAME]. What do you have to say for yourself?</English>
		<French>Que me vaut l'honneur peu enviable de votre présence ?</French>
		<German>Was verschafft mir die zweifelhafte Ehre Eures Besuchs?</German>
		<Italian>E a cosa devo il dubbio onore della tua presenza?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y a qué debemos el dudoso honor de vuestra compañía?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_LINCOLN_2</Tag>
		<English>If once you forfeit the confidence of your fellow man, you can never regain their respect and esteem. I don't have much time for you, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Que me vaut l'honneur peu enviable de votre présence ?</French>
		<German>Was verschafft mir die zweifelhafte Ehre Eures Besuchs?</German>
		<Italian>E a cosa devo il dubbio onore della tua presenza?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y a qué debemos el dudoso honor de vuestra compañía?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_LINCOLN_1</Tag>
		<English>You are ambitious, [CT_NAME], which within reasonable bounds does good rather than harm. I do hope, however, that your ambition will not cause you to deny us this?</English>
		<French>Pourriez-vous donner ceci à un bon ami, [CT_NAME] ?</French>
		<German>Ihr werdet einem treuen Freund diese kleine Bitte doch nicht abschlagen, [CT_NAME]?</German>
		<Italian>Avresti un po' di questi in nome della nostra amicizia, [CT_NAME]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Podríais darles esto a unos buenos amigos, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_LINCOLN_1</Tag>
		<English>He has a right to criticise, who has a heart to help.</English>
		<French>Partager, c'est le début de l'amitié, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Helfen heißt brüderlich teilen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Se ci tieni a me, condividi, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Compartir es de generosos, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_LINCOLN_1</Tag>
		<English>Most folks are about as happy as they make their minds up to be, [CT_NAME]. Be happy and hand over this, if you please.</English>
		<French>Répondez à nos exigences ou vous subirez la foudre de notre "terrible et rapide épée".</French>
		<German>Schlagt ein, wenn Ihr kein zweites Gettysburg erleben wollt! </German>
		<Italian>Dammi ciò che chiedo o proverai l'ira della nostra &quot;terribile e rapida spada.&quot; </Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos esto o sentiréis la cólera de nuestra &quot;terrible y veloz espada&quot;. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HAMMURABI_1</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_NAME], the prince, called of the God I am, making riches and increase; who conquered the four quarters of the world, made great the name of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</English>
		<French>Bonjour, étranger ! Contemplez avec crainte la majesté des [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] !</French>
		<German>Ich grüße Euch, Fremdling! Kommt und bestaunt die Pracht des Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT]!</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, straniero! Ammira stupito lo splendore di [OUR_CIV_SHORT]!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos a los que vienen de tierras lejanas. ¡Maravillaos ante la majestad de [OUR_CIV_SHORT]!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_HAMMURABI_1</Tag>
		<English>I am the salvation-bearing shepherd, whose staff is straight. Ready yourself to feel its sting.</English>
		<French>Je ne parle ni aux menteurs ni aux traîtres.</French>
		<German>Mit Lügnern und Betrügern wie Euch will ich nichts zu schaffen haben!</German>
		<Italian>Non parlo a bugiardi e truffatori.</Italian>
		<Spanish>No hablamos con embusteros y tramposos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_HAMMURABI_1</Tag>
		<English>If anyone is committing a robbery and is caught, then he shall be put to death. That is my law, and you have been convicted.</English>
		<French>Il n'y aura pas de paix tant que la tête du dernier soldat [CT_CIV_ADJ:1] ne sera pas au bout d'une lance [OUR_CIV_ADJ:2] !</French>
		<German>Es wird keinen Frieden geben, bis nicht auch das letzte Haupt eines [CT_CIV_ADJ:2] Kriegers die Spitze eines [OUR_CIV_ADJ:2] Speers ziert!</German>
		<Italian>Non ci sarà pace fino a quando anche l'ultima testa di un soldato di [CT_CIV_ADJ] non sarà su una picca [OUR_CIV_ADJ]!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No habrá paz hasta que la cabeza del último soldado [CT_CIV_ADJ:1] esté clavada en una pica [OUR_CIV_ADJ:2]!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_HAMMURABI_1</Tag>
		<English>I have not withdrawn myself from the men whom the Gods gave me to rule over. I have uprooted the enemy above and below, subdued the earth, brought prosperity to the land; a disturber was not permitted. These have been good times, [CT_NAME]. I thank you for them.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, cher [CT_NAME] ! En quoi les puissants [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] peuvent-ils aider votre humble empire ?</French>
		<German>Ich grüße Euch in Freundschaft, [CT_NAME]! Womit kann das mächtige Volk von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] Eurem bescheidenen Reich dienen?</German>
		<Italian>Salute, amico [CT_NAME]! Cosa può fare il grande [OUR_CIV_SHORT] per aiutare il tuo umile impero?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Os saludamos, amigable [CT_NAME]! ¿Qué puede hacer la poderosa tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT] por ayudar a vuestro humilde imperio?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_HAMMURABI_1</Tag>
		<English>The Gods called by name me, [OUR_NAME], the exalted prince, to bring about the rule of righteousness in the land, and to destroy the wicked and the evil-doers. You put yourself in great peril by being this close to me, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Alors ? Dépêchez-vous ! J'ai des lois à écrire !</French>
		<German>Nun? Was gibt's? Ich habe Gesetze zu erlassen!</German>
		<Italian>E quindi? Continua! Ho delle leggi da scrivere!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y bien? ¡Soltadlo de una vez! ¡Que tenemos un código que escribir!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_HAMMURABI_1</Tag>
		<English>If a herdsman to whose care cattle or sheep have been entrusted, be guilty of fraud, or sell them for money, then he shall pay the owner ten times the loss. That is my law. You have not been a good shepherd of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]'s lands, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Nous aurions besoin de votre aide, cher [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Wir könnten Eure freundliche Unterstützung gebrauchen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Potremmo avere bisogno del tuo aiuto, amico [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nos iría bien vuestra ayuda, amigable [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_HAMMURABI_1</Tag>
		<English>The king who rules among the kings of the cities, I am. My words are well considered; there is no wisdom like mine. I have though this over and concluded that this transaction would benefit both.</English>
		<French>Pouvez-vous donner ceci à un bon ami ?</French>
		<German>Könntet Ihr dies für gute Freunde erübrigen?</German>
		<Italian>Avresti un po' di questi in nome della nostra amicizia?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Podríais darles esto a unos buenos amigos?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_HAMMURABI_1</Tag>
		<English>Laws of justice [OUR_NAME] the wise king established. A righteous law and pious statute did he teach the land. [OUR_NAME], the protecting king I am. Now the law demands you pay tribute. Or [OUR_CIV_SHORT]'s protection can no longer be assured.</English>
		<French>Donnez-nous ce que nous voulons ou nous viendrons nous en emparer par la force.</French>
		<German>Gebt uns, was wir verlangen, oder wir werden kommen und es uns holen!</German>
		<Italian>Dacci ciò che vogliamo, o verremo di certo a prendercelo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos esto si no queréis que vayamos y lo cojamos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JUSTINIAN_1</Tag>
		<English>I salute you, [CT_NAME] of [CT_CIV_SHORT]! I believe myself to be a fair ruler. I would rather let the crime of the guilty go unpunished, than to condemn the innocent. Please, join me in peace.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, [CT_NAME] ! Que les cieux vous bénissent comme vous le méritez !</French>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]! Mögen die Götter Euch segnen, denn Ihr verdient ihren Segen!</German>
		<Italian>Ti do il benvenuto, [CT_NAME]! Possano i cieli benedirti quanto meriti!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Os doy la bienvenida, [CT_NAME]! Que los cielos os bendigan como merecéis.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_JUSTINIAN_1</Tag>
		<English>No!</English>
		<French>Non !</French>
		<German>Nein!</German>
		<Italian>No!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_JUSTINIAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Thank you for your kind offer, [CT_NAME], but I believe I would prefer to wipe your civilisation from the face of the earth.</English>
		<French>Je vous remercie de votre offre, [CT_NAME], mais je crois que je préfèrerais rayer votre civilisation de la carte.</French>
		<German>Danke für Euer freundliches Angebot, [CT_NAME], aber ich bevorzuge es, Eure Zivilisation vom Antlitz der Erde zu tilgen!</German>
		<Italian>Grazie per la tua cortese offerta, [CT_NAME], ma credo che preferirei cancellare la tua civiltà dalla faccia della Terra.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Gracias por vuestra amable oferta, [CT_NAME], pero creo que preferimos barrer vuestra civilización de la faz de la Tierra.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_JUSTINIAN_1</Tag>
		<English>You honour [OUR_CIV_SHORT] with your presence, [CT_NAME]. How can we assist you?</English>
		<French>Vous honorez les [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] de votre présence, [CT_NAME]. En quoi puis-je vous aider ?</French>
		<German>Ihr ehrt das Volk von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] mit Eurem Besuch, [CT_NAME]. Wie können wir Euch behilflich sein?</German>
		<Italian>Onori [OUR_CIV_SHORT] con la tua presenza, [CT_NAME]. Come possiamo aiutarti?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Honráis a [OUR_CIV_SHORT] con vuestra presencia, [CT_NAME]. ¿En qué podemos ayudaros?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_JUSTINIAN_1</Tag>
		<English>You may skip the pleasantries, [CT_NAME]. Why have you come to mighty [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</English>
		<French>Trêve de courtoisies, [CT_NAME]. Que voulez-vous aux puissants [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] ?</French>
		<German>Ihr könnt Euch die Freundlichkeiten sparen, [CT_NAME]. Warum belästigt Ihr das mächtige Volk von [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</German>
		<Italian>Salta i preliminari, [CT_NAME]. Perché vieni da [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Podéis ahorraros las cortesías, [CT_NAME]. ¿A qué habéis venido a la poderosa tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_JUSTINIAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Could you spare this for us, [CT_NAME]?</English>
		<French>Pourriez-vous nous donner ceci, [CT_NAME] ? </French>
		<German>Würdet Ihr uns dies hier überlassen, [CT_NAME]?</German>
		<Italian>Hai un po' di tempo per noi, [CT_NAME]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Podríais darnos esto, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_JUSTINIAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Please give us this, [CT_NAME]. It will help to ensure continued friendship between our two great empires.</English>
		<French>Veuillez nous donner ceci, [CT_NAME]. Cela renforcera l'amitié entre nos deux grands empires.</French>
		<German>Bitte gebt uns, worum wir Euch bitten, [CT_NAME]. Diese Geste wird zweifellos zur fortgesetzten Freundschaft unserer großen Reiche beitragen.</German>
		<Italian>Per favore dacci questo, [CT_NAME]. Farà in modo che l'amicizia tra i nostri due imperi continui.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Haced el favor de darnos esto, [CT_NAME]. Contribuirá a que prosiga la amistad entre nuestros dos grandes imperios.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_JUSTINIAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Give us what we want, [CT_NAME]. Your armies are no match for ours. You know this to be true.</English>
		<French>Donnez-nous ce que nous voulons, [CT_NAME]. Vos armées ne font pas le poids face aux nôtres et vous le savez.</French>
		<German>Gebt uns, was wir verlangen, [CT_NAME]! Eure Truppen können es nicht mit unseren aufnehmen, und das wisst Ihr auch!</German>
		<Italian>Dacci ciò che vogliamo, [CT_NAME]. I tuoi eserciti non possono farcela contro di noi, e lo sai.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos lo que queremos, [CT_NAME]. Vuestros ejércitos no son rivales para los nuestros, y lo sabéis.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ZARA_YAQOB_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, traveller. These are the lands of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. In the future, when you appear before me, say: "I prostrate myself before God, who gave me as King, [OUR_NAME]."</English>
		<French>Mes respects, [CT_NAME] ! Je suis [OUR_NAME], chef des dévots [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] ! Que l'amitié entre nos deux grandes civilisations dure jusqu'à ce que nous soyons bien plus puissants que vous !</French>
		<German>Seid gegrüßt, [CT_NAME]. Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Staatsoberhaupt des gottesfürchtigen [OUR_CIV_ADJ:2] Volkes! Möge die Freundschaft zwischen unseren großartigen Nationen andauern, bis wir Euch haushoch überlegen sind! </German>
		<Italian>Salute a te, [CT_NAME]. Sono [OUR_NAME], signore del popolo [OUR_CIV_ADJ], timorato di Dio! Possa l'amicizia tra le nostre due grandi civiltà durare fino a quando non saremo molto più vasti di voi! </Italian>
		<Spanish>Mis saludos, [CT_NAME]. Soy [OUR_NAME], gobernante del pueblo [OUR_CIV_ADJ:1], temeroso de Dios. Que la amistad entre nuestras dos magníficas civilizaciones perdure hasta que nosotros seamos mucho más grandes que vosotros. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_ZARA_YAQOB_1</Tag>
		<English>Be gone, you heathen fool!</English>
		<French>Hors de ma vue, païen !</French>
		<German>Hinfort mit Euch, heidnisches Wesen!</German>
		<Italian>Vattene, stupido selvaggio!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Largaos, escoria infiel!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_ZARA_YAQOB_1</Tag>
		<English>I have told my generals, "Bring me this rebel, bound with a strong cord, and throw him prostrate at my feet." I will see you thus soon enough.</English>
		<French>Il n'y aura pas de paix tant que votre âme torturée ne brûlera pas dans les flammes de l'enfer !</French>
		<German>Es wird keinen Frieden geben, bis Eure gepeinigte Seele in den Tiefen der Hölle schmort!</German>
		<Italian>Non ci sarà pace fino a quando la tua anima torturata non brucerà negli abissi infuocati dell'inferno!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No habrá paz hasta que vuestra torturada alma arda en las simas del averno!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_ZARA_YAQOB_1</Tag>
		<English>Today is verily a day of gladness, [CT_NAME]. Truly the glory of the birth of God has worked a miracle.</English>
		<French>Que les cieux vous bénissent, [CT_NAME] !</French>
		<German>Mögen die Götter Euch segnen, [CT_NAME]!</German>
		<Italian>Che le benedizioni del Cielo siano su di te, [CT_NAME]!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Que el Cielo os bendiga, [CT_NAME]!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_ZARA_YAQOB_1</Tag>
		<English>If you saw to it that in your provinces and districts the law of God came to pass and the works of sorcery ceased, you would not have been quite so objectionable. As it is, I can hardly look at you. What do you want?</English>
		<French>Dites ce que vous avez à dire, misérable pécheur. Je vous écoute. </French>
		<German>Sagt, was Ihr zu sagen habt, sündiges Wesen! Ich höre!</German>
		<Italian>Di' ciò che sei venuto a dire, peccatore. Sto ascoltando.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Decid lo que tengáis que decir, encarnación del pecado. Os escuchamos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_ZARA_YAQOB_1</Tag>
		<English>See how I have acted with my children; in my zeal for God, I have not spared them for having sinned. Now, say whether you consider this calvary sufficient. Or whether, indeed, you would reward me.</English>
		<French>Payez-nous votre tribut, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Her damit, [CT_NAME]! </German>
		<Italian>Anticipa i soldi, [CT_NAME]. </Italian>
		<Spanish>Pagadlo ahora mismo, [CT_NAME]. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_ZARA_YAQOB_1</Tag>
		<English>Know you not these words of the prophet: "The King is not succoured by his numerous army, nor the hero by his personal valiance. I have put my confidence in the Lord. He will come to my aid in His mercy." If the [CT_CIV_ADJ] people show mercy toward [OUR_CIV_SHORT], the Lord will in time aid them in return.</English>
		<French>Le ciel vous ordonne de nous donner ceci, [CT_NAME]. Je vous conseille d'obéir, à moins que vous n'aimiez les éclairs.</French>
		<German>Die Götter verlangen, dass Ihr uns Tribut zollt, [CT_NAME]. Und wenn Ihr nicht vom Blitz erschlagen werden wollt, solltet Ihr ihnen Folge leisten!</German>
		<Italian>I cieli comandano che tu ci dia ciò che ci serve, [CT_NAME]. A meno che non ti piaccia essere colpito dai fulmini ti consiglio di accettare.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es voluntad del Cielo que nos deis lo siguiente, [CT_NAME]. A menos que os gusten especialmente los rayos, os apremiamos a hacerlo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_ZARA_YAQOB_1</Tag>
		<English>In your pride, you have risen against us. Keep to the right way and the right law, and abandon the bad way to which you have pledged yourself. If you refuse, we will judge you and we will deal with you as we think fit.</English>
		<French>Tout le monde a des besoins, [CT_NAME]. En l'occurrence, il nous faut un tribut, et il vous faut le satisfaire.</French>
		<German>Jeder hat doch so seine Bedürfnisse, nicht wahr, [CT_NAME]? Uns fehlt es beispielsweise an diesem hier und Ihr tätet gut daran, es uns beschaffen. </German>
		<Italian>Tutti hanno dei bisogni, [CT_NAME]. Per esempio noi abbiamo bisogno di questo, e tu hai bisogno di darcelo. </Italian>
		<Spanish>Todo el mundo tiene sus necesidades, [CT_NAME]. Por ejemplo, nosotros necesitamos lo siguiente, y vosotros necesitáis dárnoslo. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DE_GAULLE_1</Tag>
		<English>I, [OUR_NAME], welcome you and the [CT_CIV_ADJ] people. Nothing great will ever be achieved without great men. And men are great only if they are determined to be so. Are you determined to find greatness alongside [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</English>
		<French>>Moi, [OUR_NAME], détenteur du plus grand nez de l'histoire humaine, je vous souhaite la bienvenue chez les [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] !</French>
		<German>Ich, [OUR_NAME], ausgestattet mit einem der größten und schönsten Riechkolben der Menschheitsgeschichte, heiße Euch im Namen des glorreichen Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] willkommen!</German>
		<Italian>Io, [OUR_NAME], possessore di uno dei più grandi e dei migliori nasi della storia, ti do il benvenuto presso [OUR_CIV_SHORT]!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Yo, [OUR_NAME], poseedor de una de las más bellas narices de la historia de la Humanidad, os doy la bienvenida a la gloriosa tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT]!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DE_GAULLE_2</Tag>
		<English>Monseigneur [CT_NAME]? I am [OUR_NAME], leader of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. A leader must aim high, see big, judge widely, thus setting himself apart form the ordinary people who debate in narrow confines. Don't you agree?</English>
		<French>>Moi, [OUR_NAME], détenteur du plus grand nez de l'histoire humaine, je vous souhaite la bienvenue chez les [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] !</French>
		<German>Ich, [OUR_NAME], ausgestattet mit einem der größten und schönsten Riechkolben der Menschheitsgeschichte, heiße Euch im Namen des glorreichen Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] willkommen!</German>
		<Italian>Io, [OUR_NAME], possessore di uno dei più grandi e dei migliori nasi della storia, ti do il benvenuto presso [OUR_CIV_SHORT]!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Yo, [OUR_NAME], poseedor de una de las más bellas narices de la historia de la Humanidad, os doy la bienvenida a la gloriosa tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT]!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_DE_GAULLE_1</Tag>
		<English>Deliberation is the work of many men. Action, of one alone. I am busy.</English>
		<French>Il n'y a rien à discuter. Partez !</French>
		<German>Wir haben uns nichts zu sagen! Verschwindet!</German>
		<Italian>Non c'è niente da discutere. Vattene ora.</Italian>
		<Spanish>No hay nada que hablar. Marchaos ahora mismo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_DE_GAULLE_1</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_CIV_SHORT] cannot be [OUR_CIV_SHORT] without greatness. The war continues, for Glory gives herself only to those who dream of her.</English>
		<French>>Certainement pas ! L'honneur des [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] exige que cette guerre continue jusqu'à ce que vous soyez réduits en bouillie.</French>
		<German>Keinesfalls! Es gebührt der Ehre des Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT], dass dieser Krieg fortgeführt wird, bis Ihr alle im Staub liegt!</German>
		<Italian>Certo che no! L'onore di [OUR_CIV_SHORT] vuole che questa guerra continui fino a quando non sarai ridotto in pezzi molto piccoli.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Por supuesto que no! El honor de [OUR_CIV_SHORT] exige que la guerra continúe hasta que os hayamos hecho paté de foie.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_DE_GAULLE_1</Tag>
		<English>Entré, [CT_NAME]. Please sit. I wonder sometimes... How can anyone govern a nation that has two hundred and forty-six different kinds of cheese? But enough about my problems. What can I do for you?</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, [CT_NAME]. Etes-vous revenu admirer mon allure héroïque ?</French>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]. Seid Ihr gekommen, um ein weiteres Mal mein heldenhaftes Profil zu würdigen?</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, [CT_NAME]. Sei di nuovo qui per ammirare il mio eroico profilo?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. ¿Habéis vuelto a admirar mi heroico perfil?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_DE_GAULLE_2</Tag>
		<English>Greatness is a road leading towards the unknown, mon ami. I am glad we walk it together.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, [CT_NAME]. Etes-vous revenu admirer mon allure héroïque ?</French>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]. Seid Ihr gekommen, um ein weiteres Mal mein heldenhaftes Profil zu würdigen?</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, [CT_NAME]. Sei di nuovo qui per ammirare il mio eroico profilo?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. ¿Habéis vuelto a admirar mi heroico perfil?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_DE_GAULLE_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME]. I predict you will sink step by step into a bottomless quagmire, however much you spend in men and money. What do you want now?</English>
		<French>Dites ce que vous avez à dire, [CT_NAME]. Je n'ai aucune envie de passer plus de temps que nécessaire avec vous.</French>
		<German>Sagt, was Ihr zu sagen habt, [CT_NAME]! Ich habe nicht vor, mehr Zeit mit Euch zu vergeuden als unbedingt erforderlich!</German>
		<Italian>Di' ciò che hai da dire, [CT_NAME]. Non intendo passare con te più tempo di quello strettamente necessario.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Decid lo que tengáis que decir, [CT_NAME]. No deseo pasar más tiempo con vos que el absolutamente necesario.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_DE_GAULLE_2</Tag>
		<English>The better I get to know men, the more I find myself loving dogs. I've got to know you quite a lot better than I would have liked, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Dites ce que vous avez à dire, [CT_NAME]. Je n'ai aucune envie de passer plus de temps que nécessaire avec vous.</French>
		<German>Sagt, was Ihr zu sagen habt, [CT_NAME]! Ich habe nicht vor, mehr Zeit mit Euch zu vergeuden als unbedingt erforderlich!</German>
		<Italian>Di' ciò che hai da dire, [CT_NAME]. Non intendo passare con te più tempo di quello strettamente necessario.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Decid lo que tengáis que decir, [CT_NAME]. No deseo pasar más tiempo con vos que el absolutamente necesario.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_DE_GAULLE_1</Tag>
		<English>I grew up to always respect authority and respect those in charge. So I ask this of you with the greatest respect. I hope you understand.</English>
		<French>L'honneur des [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] exige que vous nous donniez ceci. Si ce n'est pas trop vous demander, bien sûr.</French>
		<German>Es gebührt der Ehre des Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT], dass Ihr uns gebt, wonach wir verlangen. Natürlich nur, wenn es Euch nicht allzu viele Umstände macht ...</German>
		<Italian>L'onore di [OUR_CIV_SHORT] impone che tu ci dia ciò di cui abbiamo bisogno. Se non è un problema, chiaramente.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El honor de [OUR_CIV_SHORT] exige que nos proporcionéis lo siguiente. Si no os importa, claro está.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_DE_GAULLE_1</Tag>
		<English>Treaties are like roses and young girls. They last while they last. How long do you think ours has got left?</English>
		<French>L'honneur des [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] exige que vous nous donniez ceci. Et on ne plaisante pas, cette fois.</French>
		<German>Es gebührt der Ehre des Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT], dass Ihr uns Tribut zollt. Diesmal ist es uns ernst damit!</German>
		<Italian>L'onore di [OUR_CIV_SHORT] impone che tu ci dia ciò di cui abbiamo bisogno. Diciamo sul serio, stavolta.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El honor de [OUR_CIV_SHORT] exige que nos proporcionéis lo siguiente. Esta vez hablamos en serio.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_DE_GAULLE_1</Tag>
		<English>I have heard your views. They do not harmonise with mine. The decision is taken unanimously. Give.</English>
		<French>L'honneur des [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] exige que vous nous donniez ceci. Sinon, nous vous anéantirons.</French>
		<German>Es gebührt der Ehre des Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT], dass Ihr uns dies hier überlasst. Andernfalls werden wir Euch vernichten müssen!</German>
		<Italian>L'onore di [OUR_CIV_SHORT] impone che tu ci dia ciò di cui abbiamo bisogno. O vi distruggeremo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El honor de [OUR_CIV_SHORT] exige que nos proporcionéis lo siguiente. O nos veremos obligados a destruiros.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PERICLES_1</Tag>
		<English>Time is the king of all men, [CT_NAME]. He is their parent and their grave, and gives them what he will and not what they want. I am [OUR_NAME]. Will you have peace with [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</English>
		<French>En tant que chef des vénérables [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3], père et mère de tout ce qui est civilisé, moi, [OUR_NAME], daigne accepter le chef des présomptueux [CT_CIV_ADJ:3] en mon auguste présence</French>
		<German>Als Staatsoberhaupt des alten Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT], dessen Ahnen bereits zivilisiert waren, heiße ich, [OUR_NAME], das Staatsoberhaupt des aufstrebenden [CT_CIV_ADJ:2] Volkes in meiner erhabenen Pracht willkommen.</German>
		<Italian>Quale leader dell'antica civiltà di [OUR_CIV_SHORT], padre e madre di tutto ciò che è civilizzato io, [OUR_NAME], accolgo il capo della crescente popolazione [CT_CIV_ADJ] alla mia augusta presenza.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Como líder de la antigua tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT], cuna de la civilización, yo, [OUR_NAME], os doy la bienvenida, oh, líder del pueblo [CT_CIV_ADJ:1], ante mi augusta presencia.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PERICLES_2</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME], they tell me you are the leader of the [CT_CIV_ADJ]. Remember, what you leave behind is not what is engraved in stone monuments, but what is woven into the lives of others. Make a good weave -- make peace with [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</English>
		<French>En tant que chef des vénérables [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3], père et mère de tout ce qui est civilisé, moi, [OUR_NAME], daigne accepter le chef des présomptueux [CT_CIV_ADJ:3] en mon auguste présence</French>
		<German>Als Staatsoberhaupt des alten Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT], dessen Ahnen bereits zivilisiert waren, heiße ich, [OUR_NAME], das Staatsoberhaupt des aufstrebenden [CT_CIV_ADJ:2] Volkes in meiner erhabenen Pracht willkommen.</German>
		<Italian>Quale leader dell'antica civiltà di [OUR_CIV_SHORT], padre e madre di tutto ciò che è civilizzato io, [OUR_NAME], accolgo il capo della crescente popolazione [CT_CIV_ADJ] alla mia augusta presenza.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Como líder de la antigua tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT], cuna de la civilización, yo, [OUR_NAME], os doy la bienvenida, oh, líder del pueblo [CT_CIV_ADJ:1], ante mi augusta presencia.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_PERICLES_1</Tag>
		<English>Heroes have the whole earth for their tomb. Whose grave are you treading on? Go away and look for the answer.</English>
		<French>Non !</French>
		<German>Nein!</German>
		<Italian>No!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_PERICLES_1</Tag>
		<English>Freedom is the sure possession of those alone who have the courage to defend it. [OUR_CIV_SHORT] will never give up her freedom. The war must go on.</English>
		<French>La paix ? Ne soyez pas ridicule. Il ne peut y avoir de paix entre des êtres civilisés et des barbares.</French>
		<German>Frieden? Seid nicht albern! Zwischen zivilisierten Menschen und Barbaren kann es keinen Frieden geben! </German>
		<Italian>Pace? Non essere stupido. Non può esserci pace tra civilizzato e barbaro. </Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Paz? No seáis tan idiota. No puede haber paz entre la civilización y los bárbaros. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_PERICLES_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME], do enter! We are alike, you and I. Our love of what is beautiful does not lead to extravagance; our love of the things of the mind does not make us soft.</English>
		<French>Vous revoilà, [CT_NAME] ? Merveilleux ! Asseyons-nous sur un rondin et débattons de métaphysique aristotélicienne, voulez-vous ?</French>
		<German>Ihr besucht uns erneut, [CT_NAME]? Wunderbar! Lasst uns Platz nehmen und über die Metaphysik des Aristoteles diskutieren, bis es Schlafenszeit ist, in Ordnung?</German>
		<Italian>Di nuovo qui, [CT_NAME]? Magnifico! Sediamoci su un tronco e discutiamo della metafisica aristotelica fino a sera, vuoi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Habéis vuelto, [CT_NAME]? ¡Fantástico! Sentémonos y debatamos sobre metafísica aristotélica hasta que caiga la noche, ¿hace?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_PERICLES_2</Tag>
		<English>My friend. It is good that we do not fight. Trees, though they are cut and loped, grow up again. But if men are destroyed, it is not easy to find new ones.</English>
		<French>Vous revoilà, [CT_NAME] ? Merveilleux ! Asseyons-nous sur un rondin et débattons de métaphysique aristotélicienne, voulez-vous ?</French>
		<German>Ihr besucht uns erneut, [CT_NAME]? Wunderbar! Lasst uns Platz nehmen und über die Metaphysik des Aristoteles diskutieren, bis es Schlafenszeit ist, in Ordnung?</German>
		<Italian>Di nuovo qui, [CT_NAME]? Magnifico! Sediamoci su un tronco e discutiamo della metafisica aristotelica fino a sera, vuoi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Habéis vuelto, [CT_NAME]? ¡Fantástico! Sentémonos y debatamos sobre metafísica aristotélica hasta que caiga la noche, ¿hace?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_PERICLES_1</Tag>
		<English>Having knowledge but lacking the power to express it clearly is no better than never having any ideas at all. Are you just inarticulate, or are you actually stupid, I wonder?</English>
		<French>Alors ? Parlez !</French>
		<German>Nun? Raus damit!</German>
		<Italian>Be'? Sputa il rospo!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y bien? ¡Soltadlo de una vez!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_PERICLES_2</Tag>
		<English>Time is the wisest counsellor of all, and it will show me how to destroy you. Until then: what do you want?</English>
		<French>Alors ? Parlez !</French>
		<German>Nun? Raus damit!</German>
		<Italian>Be'? Sputa il rospo!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y bien? ¡Soltadlo de una vez!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_PERICLES_1</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_CIV_SHORT] does not imitate, but is a model to others. Please help us remain so. This would be of great use to us.</English>
		<French>Les puissants [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] exigent un petit gage d'amitié de leurs loyaux alliés [CT_CIV_SHORT:3]. </French>
		<German>Das mächtige Volk von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] fordert eine kleine Geste der Freundschaft von seinen treuen Verbündeten, den Bürgern von [CT_CIV_SHORT]. </German>
		<Italian>[OUR_CIV_SHORT] richiede un piccolo gesto di amicizia da parte di [CT_CIV_SHORT], suo fedele alleato. </Italian>
		<Spanish>La poderosa tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT] solicita una pequeña muestra de amistad de su fiel aliado, el imperio de [CT_CIV_SHORT]. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_PERICLES_1</Tag>
		<English>Just because you do not take an interest in politics doesn't mean politics won't take an interest in you. It would be political of you to give us this.</English>
		<French>Un chef véritablement civilisé nous offrirait ce que nous voulons, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Ein wahrhaft zivilisiertes Staatsoberhaupt würde uns geben, was wir verlangen, [CT_NAME]. </German>
		<Italian>Un capo davvero civilizzato ci darebbe ciò che vogliamo, [CT_NAME]. </Italian>
		<Spanish>Un líder verdaderamente civilizado nos daría lo que queremos, ¿no, [CT_NAME]? </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_PERICLES_1</Tag>
		<English>Fish live in the sea, [CT_NAME], as men do on land: the great ones eat the little ones. Don't be a small fish -- give us grand tribute.</English>
		<French>Ne prenez pas les exigences des Grecs à la légère, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Nehmt Euch vor Griechen in Acht, die Geschenke von Euch fordern, [CT_NAME]! </German>
		<Italian>Attento ai Greci che chiedono doni, [CT_NAME]. </Italian>
		<Spanish>Cuidaos de los griegos que piden regalos, [CT_NAME]. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome to my court. I am [OUR_CIV_ADJ] Emperor [OUR_NAME]. Tell me about your land and your customs. What is your tongue? To have another language is to possess a second soul.</English>
		<French>Que les cieux vous bénissent, [CT_NAME] ! Moi, [OUR_NAME], chef des puissants [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] vous souhaite la bienvenue dans notre grand empire.</French>
		<German>Möge der Himmel Euch segnen, [CT_NAME]! Ich, [OUR_NAME], Staatsoberhaupt des überragenden [OUR_CIV_ADJ:2] Volkes, heiße Euch in unserem prachtvollen Reich willkommen.</German>
		<Italian>Possano discendere su di te le benedizioni del Cielo, [CT_NAME]. Io, [OUR_NAME], leader del potente popolo [OUR_CIV_ADJ], ti do il benvenuto nel nostro poderoso impero.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Que el Cielo os bendiga, [CT_NAME]. Yo, [OUR_NAME], líder del poderoso pueblo [OUR_CIV_ADJ:1], os doy la bienvenida a nuestro gran imperio.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_1</Tag>
		<English>Get out of my sight.</English>
		<French>Hors de ma vue, avant que je ne fasse quelque chose d'extrêmement peu diplomatique.</French>
		<German>Geht mir aus den Augen, bevor ich mich zu etwas gänzlich Undiplomatischem hinreißen lasse!</German>
		<Italian>Sparisci dalla mia vista prima che faccia qualcosa di molto poco diplomatico.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Fuera de mi vista antes de que haga algo muy poco diplomático.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace? The [OUR_EMPIRE] will exterminate you.</English>
		<French>La paix ? Par ma barbe, jamais !</French>
		<German>Frieden? Bei meinem Barthaar: Auf keinen Fall!</German>
		<Italian>Pace? Nemmeno per i peli della mia barba!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Paz? ¡Por los pelos de mi barba! ¡No!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_1</Tag>
		<English>We graciously welcome the mighty leader of [OUR_CIV_SHORT] to our presence.</English>
		<French>Nous accueillons gracieusement le puissant chef des [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] parmi nous.</French>
		<German>Wir heißen das mächtige Staatsoberhaupt des Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] gnädigerweise willkommen.</German>
		<Italian>Accogliamo con grazia il grande leader di [OUR_CIV_SHORT] alla nostra presenza.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Os damos una cordial bienvenida ante nuestra presencia, oh, líder de la poderosa tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_1</Tag>
		<English>What do YOU want, knave?</English>
		<French>Que voulez-vous, manant ?</French>
		<German>Was wollt IHR denn, Gauner?</German>
		<Italian>Che COSA vuoi, furfante?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Qué queréis, canalla?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_CHARLEMAGNE_1</Tag>
		<English>Share the wealth?</English>
		<French>Je veux ma part du gâteau.</French>
		<German>Lasst uns doch nur ein wenig an Eurem Wohlstand teilhaben ... bitte?</German>
		<Italian>Condividi un po' di ricchezza, eh?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Compartid un poco de riqueza, ¿no?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_CHARLEMAGNE_1</Tag>
		<English>I believe that you'll find it in [CT_CIV_SHORT]'s best interest to supply us with the following.</English>
		<French>Vous comprendrez aisément qu'il est dans l'intérêt des [CT_CIV_SHORT:3] de nous donner ceci.</French>
		<German>Ich denke, es wäre im besten Interesse des Volkes von [CT_CIV_SHORT], uns Tribut zu zollen, findet Ihr nicht auch?</German>
		<Italian>Credo che scoprirai che darci ciò che chiediamo è nell'interesse di [CT_CIV_SHORT].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Creo que a [CT_CIV_SHORT] le interesa mucho proporcionarnos lo siguiente.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_CHARLEMAGNE_1</Tag>
		<English>Give us what we want and perhaps your heathenish empire will survive another day. Perhaps...</English>
		<French>Donnez-nous ce que nous voulons et nous laisserons votre empire barbare survivre un jour de plus. Enfin, peut-être...</French>
		<German>Wenn Ihr uns gebt, was wir verlangen, wird Euer heidnisches Volk möglicherweise noch eine Weile überdauern. Möglicherweise ...</German>
		<Italian>Dacci ciò che vogliamo e forse il tuo impero pagano sopravvivrà un altro giorno. Forse...</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos lo que queremos y quizá vuestro imperio infiel sobreviva otro día. Quizá...</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SURYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME], I have heard of you. Know that the people of [OUR_CIV_SHORT] have sworn to me, [OUR_NAME], their lives and devotion gratefully. They will not revere another king, nor be accomplices of any enemy. If there is war, they will fight and risk life. Bearing that in mind, will you agree to peace?</English>
		<French>Je suis ravi de vous rencontrer, [CT_NAME], et je me réjouis à l'idée de longues années de paix et d'amitié entre nous.</French>
		<German>Ich freue mich, Euch zu sehen, [CT_NAME], und ich freue mich auch auf viele zukünftige Jahre des Friedens und der Freundschaft zwischen unseren großen Nationen.</German>
		<Italian>Sono contento di incontrarti, [CT_NAME], e vedo davanti a noi molti anni di pace e amicizia tra le nostre due grandi nazioni.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Estamos encantadísimos de conoceros, [CT_NAME], y deseamos muchos años de amistad entre nuestras dos grandes naciones.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SURYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>I will not speak with you.</English>
		<French>Laissez-moi tranquille, sale barbare !</French>
		<German>Lasst mich in Ruhe, barbarischer Abschaum!</German>
		<Italian>Lasciami in pace, cane barbaro!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Dejadnos en paz, escoria bárbara!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SURYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>We do not make peace with barbarians.</English>
		<French>Nous ne faisons pas la paix avec les barbares.</French>
		<German>Wir schließen keinen Frieden mit Barbaren!</German>
		<Italian>Non facciamo pace con i barbari.</Italian>
		<Spanish>No firmamos la paz con bárbaros.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SURYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, my friend! Let us discuss many things. Have some fruit. Be happy.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, mon ami ! Discutons un instant. Tenez, prenez une mangue.</French>
		<German>Ich grüße Euch in Freundschaft! Lasst uns doch ein wenig plaudern. Hier, kostet eine Mango!</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, amico mio! Abbiamo molto di cui discutere. Ecco: prenditi un mango.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Os saludamos, camarada! Hemos de hablar de muchas cosas. Tomad un mango.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SURYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Well?</English>
		<French>Eh bien ?</French>
		<German>Nun?</German>
		<Italian>Quindi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y bien?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SURYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>The [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people could use your assistance, [CT_NAME]. I trust that you won't disappoint them.</English>
		<French>Les [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] ont besoin de votre aide, [CT_NAME]. J'espère que vous ne les décevrez pas.</French>
		<German>Das [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] Volk könnte Eure Hilfe gebrauchen, [CT_NAME]. Ihr werdet es doch sicher nicht enttäuschen wollen ...</German>
		<Italian>Al popolo [OUR_CIV_ADJ] farebbe comodo il tuo aiuto, [CT_NAME]. Spero che non vorrai deluderla.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al pueblo [OUR_CIV_ADJ:1] le iría bien vuestra ayuda, [CT_NAME]. Confiamos en que no nos decepcionaréis.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SURYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>You are wealthy, [CT_NAME], wealthy enough to give.</English>
		<French>On se partage le butin, mon pote ?</French>
		<German>Seid Ihr bereit, Euren Reichtum zu teilen?</German>
		<Italian>Condividi la tua ricchezza, Baby?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Compartid la riqueza, porfi.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SURYAVARMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>You may pay us in treasure today or in blood tomorrow.</English>
		<French>Vous avez le choix entre nous payer en or aujourd'hui ou en sang demain. Je vous recommande fortement la première option.</French>
		<German>Ihr habt die Wahl: Überschüttet uns heute mit Reichtümern oder zahlt morgen mit Eurem Blut. Ich persönlich würde Euch eindringlich zu Ersterem raten ...</German>
		<Italian>Puoi pagarci col tesoro oggi o col sangue domani. Ti consiglio caldamente il primo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>O nos pagáis en tesoro hoy o en sangre mañana. Os recomiendo encarecidamente lo primero.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PACAL_1</Tag>
		<English>Sun-faced Janaab [OUR_NAME] welcomes you to the land of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Let us swear to peace.</English>
		<French>Je vous salue, [CT_NAME]. Les [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] sont puissants. Agissez loyalement avec nous et vous prospèrerez. Attaquez-nous et le sang de vos guerriers teindra en rouge les façades de nos temples !</French>
		<German>Ich grüße Euch, [CT_NAME]. Das Volk von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] ist mächtig - behandelt uns fair, dann soll es Euer Schaden nicht sein. Solltet Ihr uns jedoch angreifen, werden wir unsere Tempel mit dem Blut Eurer Krieger tränken!</German>
		<Italian>Ti saluto, [CT_NAME]. [OUR_CIV_SHORT] è una potente civiltà: sii giusto con noi e prospererai. Attaccaci e i nostri templi diverranno rossi col sangue dei tuoi guerrieri!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Os saludo, [CT_NAME]. [OUR_CIV_SHORT] es una tierra poderosa: tratadnos como se debe y prosperaréis. ¡Atacadnos y en nuestros templos correrá la sangre de vuestros guerreros!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_PACAL_1</Tag>
		<English>No! I do not want your presence.</English>
		<French>Non ! Je suis bien trop important pour parler avec vous !</French>
		<German>Nein! Ich bin eine viel zu bedeutende Persönlichkeit, als dass ich mich mit Euch abgeben würde!</German>
		<Italian>No! Sono troppo importante per parlare con te!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No! ¡Soy demasiado importante como para hablar con vos!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_PACAL_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace now? Oh no.</English>
		<French>La paix maintenant ? Vous rigolez ?</French>
		<German>Frieden? Jetzt? Das soll wohl ein Witz sein!</German>
		<Italian>Pace, ora? Stai scherzando!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Ahora queréis la paz? ¡Debéis de estar de guasa!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_PACAL_1</Tag>
		<English>I greet my friend and equal. Let us exchange gifts.</English>
		<French>Je salue mon ami et quasi égal, [CT_NAME]. Alors, qu'allez-vous nous offrir aujourd'hui ?</French>
		<German>Ich grüße Euch in Freundschaft und als nahezu ebenbürtiges Staatsoberhaupt, [CT_NAME]. Und? Womit wollt Ihr uns heute erfreuen?</German>
		<Italian>Saluto il mio amico e quasi mio pari, [CT_NAME]. E che regalo vuoi farci, oggi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludo a mi casi igual e inseparable amistad, [CT_NAME]. ¿Y qué presente nos traéis hoy?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_PACAL_1</Tag>
		<English>Come to grovel have you?</English>
		<French>Venu ramper à nos pieds, hein ? Bon, je vous écoute.</French>
		<German>Seid Ihr gekommen, um vor uns zu kriechen? Nun denn, nur zu!</German>
		<Italian>Sei venuto a strisciare ai nostri piedi, eh? Be', fai pure.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Venís a postraros a nuestros pies, eh? Bueno, adelante.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_PACAL_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME], a war between our two great peoples must be avoided at all costs, don't you agree?</English>
		<French>[CT_NAME], la guerre entre nos deux grandes nations doit à tout prix être évitée, vous ne croyez pas ? Alors, payez !</French>
		<German>Es ist doch sicher auch in Eurem Sinne, einen Krieg zwischen unseren Völkern zu vermeiden, nicht wahr, [CT_NAME]? Also, her damit!</German>
		<Italian>[CT_NAME], dovremmo evitare a tutti i costi una guerra tra i nostri due grandi popoli, non sei d'accordo? Allora paga.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[CT_NAME], hay que evitar a toda costa una guerra entre nuestros pueblos, ¿no creéis? Pues pagad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_PACAL_1</Tag>
		<English>Giving us what we want is the only way to avoid immediate destruction.</English>
		<French>Donnez-nous ce que nous voulons. C'est le seul moyen d'éviter l'anéantissement immédiat. Payez !</French>
		<German>Der einzige Weg, Eure sofortige Vernichtung zu verhindern, ist, unsere Forderung zu erfüllen. Also, her damit!</German>
		<Italian>Darci ciò che chiediamo è l'unico modo per evitare la distruzione immediata. Paga.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Darnos lo que queremos es la única manera de evitar una destrucción inmediata. Pagad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_PACAL_1</Tag>
		<English>Give us what we want or prepare for your journey to the underworld.</English>
		<French>Donnez-nous ce que nous voulons ou mourez !</French>
		<German>Gebt uns, wonach wir verlangen, oder sterbt!</German>
		<Italian>Dacci ciò che vogliamo o morirai.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos lo que queremos o morid.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SITTING_BULL_1</Tag>
		<English>Behold, my friend, the spring is come; the earth has gladly received the embrace of the sun, and we shall soon see the results of their love! I am [OUR_NAME], Great Chief of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I greet you in peace.</English>
		<French>Les puissants [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] vous souhaitent la bienvenue, [CT_NAME]. Serait-il politiquement correct de vous offrir un calumet de la paix ?</French>
		<German>Das großartige [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] Volk heißt Euch willkommen, [CT_NAME]. Wäre es politisch korrekt, Euch die Friedenspfeife anzubieten?</German>
		<Italian>Il grande popolo [OUR_CIV_ADJ] ti dà il benvenuto, [CT_NAME]. È politicamente corretto offrirti un calumet della pace?</Italian>
		<Spanish>El gran pueblo [OUR_CIV_ADJ:1] os da la bienvenida, [CT_NAME]. ¿Sería apropiado ofreceros una pipa de la paz u os habéis sumado a la cruzada contra el tabaco?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SITTING_BULL_2</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, stranger. I am [OUR_NAME]. I am here by the will of the God, and by His will I am chief. Are our peoples to fight or to trade?</English>
		<French>Les puissants [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] vous souhaitent la bienvenue, [CT_NAME]. Serait-il politiquement correct de vous offrir un calumet de la paix ?</French>
		<German>Das großartige [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] Volk heißt Euch willkommen, [CT_NAME]. Wäre es politisch korrekt, Euch die Friedenspfeife anzubieten?</German>
		<Italian>Il grande popolo [OUR_CIV_ADJ] ti dà il benvenuto, [CT_NAME]. È politicamente corretto offrirti un calumet della pace?</Italian>
		<Spanish>El gran pueblo [OUR_CIV_ADJ:1] os da la bienvenida, [CT_NAME]. ¿Sería apropiado ofreceros una pipa de la paz u os habéis sumado a la cruzada contra el tabaco?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SITTING_BULL_1</Tag>
		<English>It is not necessary for eagles to be crows.</English>
		<French>Je ne parle pas aux menteurs. Maintenant, filez !</French>
		<German>Ich gebe mich nicht mit Lügnern ab! Und jetzt verschwindet!</German>
		<Italian>Non parlo coi bugiardi. Ora sgomma.</Italian>
		<Spanish>No hablo con gente embustera. Y ahora, largo de aquí.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SITTING_BULL_1</Tag>
		<English>If I agree to dispose of any part of our land to the [CT_CIV_ADJ] people, I would feel guilty of taking food away from our children's mouths. I do not wish to be that mean. The war must continue.</English>
		<French>Cette guerre prendra fin quand je le déciderai et pas avant.</French>
		<German>Dieser Krieg wird erst enden, wenn ich es sage, und nicht einen Augenblick früher!</German>
		<Italian>Questa guerra finirà quando io deciderò di farla finire, e non un secondo prima.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta guerra terminará cuando yo lo decida, y no antes.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SITTING_BULL_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, my friend! Let us put our minds together and see what life we can make for our children.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, mon ami ! Je vous félicite d'avoir eu la sagesse de chercher conseil auprès de civilisations plus évoluées.</French>
		<German>Willkommen! Ihr seid in der Tat gut beraten, Euch mit jenen, die Euch überlegen sind, gutzustellen.</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, amico mio! Sei davvero saggio a cercare consiglio presso chi è migliore di te.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Os saludamos, camarada! Tenéis sabiduría suficiente como para buscar consejo de vuestros superiores.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SITTING_BULL_2</Tag>
		<English>Well met, friend. It is spring! Every seed is awakened, and all animal life. Tell me -- what can I do for you this day?</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, mon ami ! Je vous félicite d'avoir eu la sagesse de chercher conseil auprès de civilisations plus évoluées.</French>
		<German>Willkommen! Ihr seid in der Tat gut beraten, Euch mit jenen, die Euch überlegen sind, gutzustellen.</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, amico mio! Sei davvero saggio a cercare consiglio presso chi è migliore di te.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Os saludamos, camarada! Tenéis sabiduría suficiente como para buscar consejo de vuestros superiores.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SITTING_BULL_1</Tag>
		<English>There are things the [CT_CIV_ADJ] tell us that sound good to hear. But when they have accomplished their purpose they go home and do not try to fulfill their agreements with us. I will listen to you, but wearily.</English>
		<French>Que pourriez-vous dire qui soit du moindre intérêt pour moi ?</French>
		<German>Was könntet Ihr mir schon zu bieten haben?</German>
		<Italian>Cosa potresti mai dire di minimamente interessante per me?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Qué podéis decir que tenga siquiera el mínimo interés para mí?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SITTING_BULL_2</Tag>
		<English>Each man is good in the sight of the God, [CT_NAME]. In my sight, however... I struggle when I see you.</English>
		<French>Que pourriez-vous dire qui soit du moindre intérêt pour moi ?</French>
		<German>Was könntet Ihr mir schon zu bieten haben?</German>
		<Italian>Cosa potresti mai dire di minimamente interessante per me?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Qué podéis decir que tenga siquiera el mínimo interés para mí?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SITTING_BULL_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME], you claim this mother of ours, the earth, for your own use. But will you not share a little?</English>
		<French>Voudriez-vous partager votre richesse avec vos amis et alliés, [CT_NAME] ?</French>
		<German>Wärt Ihr bereit, Euren Wohlstand mit guten Freunden und verlässlichen Verbündeten zu teilen, [CT_NAME]?</German>
		<Italian>Vuoi condividere un po' delle tue ricchezze con i tuoi buoni amici e alleati, [CT_NAME]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Os importaría compartir parte de vuestra riqueza con vuestros amigos y aliados, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SITTING_BULL_1</Tag>
		<English>The [CT_CIV_ADJ] know how to make everything, but not how to distribute it. Or would you prove me wrong?</English>
		<French>Au nom de l'amitié qui lie nos grands peuples, j'exige que vous nous donniez ceci en gage d'estime. </French>
		<German>Zum Wohle der fortgesetzten Freundschaft unserer großartigen Völker fordere ich ein Zeichen Eurer Anerkennung!</German>
		<Italian>Per il bene della duratura amicizia tra i nostri grandi popoli ti chiedo ciò di cui abbiamo bisogno come segno di riconoscimento.</Italian>
		<Spanish>En aras de que continúe la amistad entre nuestros dos grandes pueblos, os solicito una muestra de vuestro aprecio.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SITTING_BULL_1</Tag>
		<English>God put in your heart certain wishes and plans; in my heart He put different desires. You must give the [OUR_EMPIRE] this.</English>
		<French>Il n'est pas sage de priver de nourriture un ours affamé, [CT_NAME]. Vous risquez de vous faire déchiqueter. </French>
		<German>Es wäre nicht besonders klug, einem hungrigen Bär sein Futter zu verweigern, [CT_NAME]. Ihr würdet Euch nur selbst schaden.</German>
		<Italian>Non è saggio negare il cibo a un orso affamato, [CT_NAME]. Rischi di prenderle.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es poco prudente quitarle la comida a un oso hambriento, [CT_NAME]. Si os ataca, será culpa vuestra.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WILLEM_VAN_ORANJE_1</Tag>
		<English>I am honoured to meet you, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], though some call me 'the Silent'. I am not silent, I merely watch my tongue. I hope our nations will have peace.</English>
		<French>Je suis honoré de vous rencontrer, [CT_NAME]. J'espère que nos deux nations seront capables de vivre dans la paix et l'amitié.</French>
		<German>Es ist mir eine Ehre, [CT_NAME]. Ich hoffe, es wird Friede und Freundschaft zwischen unseren Völkern herrschen.</German>
		<Italian>È un onore incontrarti, [CT_NAME]. Spero che le nostre due nazioni riusciranno a vivere in pace e amicizia.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es un honor conoceros, [CT_NAME]. Espero que nuestras dos naciones sean capaces de vivir en paz y armonía.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_WILLEM_VAN_ORANJE_1</Tag>
		<English>No!</English>
		<French>Non !</French>
		<German>Nein!</German>
		<Italian>No!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_WILLEM_VAN_ORANJE_1</Tag>
		<English>Certainly not. The war will continue until we have achieved total victory.</English>
		<French>Certainement pas. La guerre continuera jusqu'à la victoire totale.</French>
		<German>Auf keinen Fall! Der Krieg wird so lange fortgeführt, bis wir den vollständigen Sieg erzielt haben!</German>
		<Italian>Certo che no. La guerra continuerà fino a quando non avremo ottenuto una vittoria totale.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Por supuesto que no. La guerra seguirá hasta que hayamos logrado la victoria total.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_WILLEM_VAN_ORANJE_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, [CT_NAME]. I can always spare a few moments to converse with friends and allies.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, [CT_NAME]. Je suis toujours disponible pour discuter avec mes amis et alliés.</French>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]. Für Freunde und Verbündete habe ich doch immer ein paar Minuten Zeit.</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, [CT_NAME]. Ho sempre un momento da dedicare ad amici e alleati.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Siempre tengo un momento libre para charlar con amigos y aliados como vos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_WILLEM_VAN_ORANJE_1</Tag>
		<English>My God, have pity on my soul; my God, have pity on this poor people. It is bloody [CT_CIV_SHORT] come calling.</English>
		<French>Je vous écoute.</French>
		<German>Ich höre!</German>
		<Italian>Sto ascoltando.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Os escuchamos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_WILLEM_VAN_ORANJE_1</Tag>
		<English>Can you spare us this, [CT_NAME]? I would be extremely grateful for your assistance.</English>
		<French>Pouvez-vous nous donner ceci, [CT_NAME] ? Je vous serais extrêmement reconnaissant de votre aide.</French>
		<German>Könnt Ihr das hier erübrigen, [CT_NAME]? Ich wäre Euch wirklich außerordentlich verbunden.</German>
		<Italian>Puoi darci ciò che chiediamo, [CT_NAME]? Sarei molto riconoscente per la tua assistenza.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Podrías darnos esto, [CT_NAME]? Os estaríamos tremendamente agradecidos por vuestra ayuda.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_WILLEM_VAN_ORANJE_1</Tag>
		<English>It would be diplomatically expedient for you to give us what we want, [CT_NAME]?</English>
		<French>Il serait diplomatiquement opportun de nous donner ce que nous voulons, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Es wäre in diplomatischer Hinsicht durchaus angebracht, unsere Forderung zu erfüllen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Sarebbe diplomaticamente vantaggioso darci ciò che vogliamo, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿No sería más oportuno, diplomáticamente hablando, que nos dierais lo que queremos, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_WILLEM_VAN_ORANJE_1</Tag>
		<English>Time to pay the piper, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Il est temps de payer l'ardoise, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Zeit, die Zeche zu zahlen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>È ora di pagare il conto, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es hora de pagar a quienes tienen la sartén por el mango, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SULEIMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>I, [OUR_NAME], am the sultan of sultans, the strongest ruler, the loftiest king who defeats kingdoms around the world, the shadow of God, the son of Sultan Selim Khan. You are the ruler of the province of [CT_CIV_SHORT]. I will grant you peace.</English>
		<French>Ravi de vous rencontrer, [CT_NAME] ! Je suis [OUR_NAME] le Magnifique. Asseyez-vous à mes côtés pour baigner dans ma gloire.</French>
		<German>Wohlan, [CT_NAME]! Ich bin [OUR_NAME], auch Euer Prächtigkeit genannt. Kommt, setzt Euch und sonnt Euch in meinem Glanze, während wir ein paar Dinge besprechen.</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, [CT_NAME]! Sono [OUR_NAME] il Magnifico. Vieni: siedi e beati della mia gloria mentre discutiamo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Nos llena de dicha conoceros, [CT_NAME]! Soy [OUR_NAME] el Magnífico. Venid, sentaos y daos un baño de mi gloria mientras hablamos de muchas cosas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SULEIMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Not a chance.</English>
		<French>Aucune chance.</French>
		<German>Keine Chance!</German>
		<Italian>Nemmeno per sogno.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ni en broma.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SULEIMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>That would be unwise at the moment. The war shall continue.</English>
		<French>Ce ne serait pas avisé pour le moment. La guerre continuera.</French>
		<German>Das wäre gegenwärtig unklug. Der Krieg wird fortgesetzt!</German>
		<Italian>Non sarebbe saggio, al momento. La guerra continuerà.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sería muy poco aconsejable en este momento. La guerra proseguirá.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SULEIMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>My palace is always open to you, [CT_NAME], oh wise and generous leader of [CT_CIV_SHORT].</English>
		<French>Mon palais vous est toujours ouvert, [CT_NAME], ô sage et généreux chef des [CT_CIV_SHORT:3].</French>
		<German>Mein Palast steht Euch immer offen, [CT_NAME], weises und großzügiges Staatsoberhaupt von [CT_CIV_SHORT].</German>
		<Italian>Il mio palazzo è sempre aperto per te, [CT_NAME], saggio e generoso governante di [CT_CIV_SHORT].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mi palacio siempre está abierto para vos, [CT_NAME], oh, líder de [CT_CIV_SHORT], espejo de sabiduría y generosidad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SULEIMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Well? Get on with it! Every moment that I spend gazing upon your wizened visage is painful to me.</English>
		<French>Eh bien ? Parlez ! Chaque moment que je passe à contempler votre visage ratatiné m'est affreusement pénible.</French>
		<German>Nun? Redet schon! Jeder Augenblick, den ich Eure schrumpelige Visage betrachten muss, ist mir ein Gräuel!</German>
		<Italian>Allora? Datti una mossa! Ogni momento passato a guardare il tuo viso raggrinzito è una tortura, per me.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y bien? ¡Soltadlo de una vez! Me duele cada segundo que paso mirando vuestra marchita figura.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SULEIMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Would you care to give [OUR_CIV_SHORT] a small token of your affection, [CT_NAME]?</English>
		<French>Auriez-vous l'obligeance d'offrir aux [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] un petit gage de votre affection, [CT_NAME] ?</French>
		<German>Was haltet Ihr davon, die Bürger von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] mit einer Geste der Ehrerbietung zu erfreuen, [CT_NAME]?</German>
		<Italian>Che ne diresti di dare a [OUR_CIV_ADJ] un piccolo segno di amicizia, [CT_NAME]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Os importaría darle a [OUR_CIV_SHORT] una pequeña muestra de vuestro aprecio, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SULEIMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>It is wise for inferior cultures to shower their betters with gifts, don't you think?</English>
		<French>Vous ne trouvez pas qu'il est sage de couvrir de cadeaux les civilisations supérieures ?</French>
		<German>Unterlegene Kulturen sind gut beraten, die ihnen überlegenen Völker zu beschenken, findet Ihr nicht auch?</German>
		<Italian>È saggio, per le culture inferiori, riempire di regali chi è migliore di loro, non trovi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es juicioso que las culturas inferiores colmen de regalos a las superiores, ¿no creéis?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SULEIMAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Our protection comes at a price, [CT_NAME]. Pay up or suffer the consequences.</English>
		<French>Notre protection a un prix, [CT_NAME]. Payez ou vous en subirez les conséquences.</French>
		<German>Unser Schutz ist nicht umsonst zu haben, [CT_NAME]! Also zahlt oder tragt die Konsequenzen!</German>
		<Italian>La nostra protezione ha un prezzo, [CT_NAME]. Dacci ciò che vogliamo o pagane le conseguenze.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nuestra protección tiene un precio, [CT_NAME]. Pagad o afrontad las consecuencias.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DARIUS_1</Tag>
		<English>I, King [OUR_NAME], put forth unto all people, nations, and languages that dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied unto you.</English>
		<French>Moi, [OUR_NAME], souhaite la bienvenue à [CT_NAME], chef de la présomptueuse nation des [CT_CIV_SHORT:3].</French>
		<German>Ich, [OUR_NAME], heiße Euch willkommen, [CT_NAME], Staatsoberhaupt des aufstrebenden Volkes von [CT_CIV_SHORT].</German>
		<Italian>Io, [OUR_NAME], do il benvenuto a [CT_NAME], signore della giovane civiltà di [CT_CIV_SHORT].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Yo, [OUR_NAME], doy la bienvenida a [CT_NAME], dirigente de la advenediza nación de [CT_CIV_SHORT].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_DARIUS_1</Tag>
		<English>I will not speak with you!</English>
		<French>Je ne veux pas vous parler !</French>
		<German>Ich werde nicht mit Euch reden!</German>
		<Italian>Non parlerò con te!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No hablo con vos!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_DARIUS_1</Tag>
		<English>Your grovelling will not save your people from destruction.</English>
		<French>Suppliez-moi tant que vous voulez, [CT_NAME]. Je ne sauverai pas votre misérable peuple de l'anéantissement !</French>
		<German>Kriecht so viel vor mir herum, wie Ihr wollt, [CT_NAME], doch das wird Euer erbärmliches Volk auch nicht vor der Vernichtung bewahren!</German>
		<Italian>Umiliati quanto ti pare, [CT_NAME]. Non salverò dalla distruzione il tuo pietoso popolo!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Humillaos cuanto queráis, [CT_NAME]. ¡Eso no salvará de la destrucción a vuestro lastimero pueblo!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_DARIUS_1</Tag>
		<English>You return, [CT_NAME]. I am glad.</English>
		<French>Vous revoilà, hein ? Qu'est-ce qu'il y a encore ?</French>
		<German>Schon wieder Ihr? Nun, worum geht es diesmal?</German>
		<Italian>Sei ancora qui, eh? Che succede questa volta?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ya estáis de vuelta, ¿eh? ¿De qué se trata esta vez?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_DARIUS_1</Tag>
		<English>I have no wish to speak with you.</English>
		<French>Tiens, tiens, regardez qui voilà...</French>
		<German>Sieh einer an, wer da hereingeschneit kommt!</German>
		<Italian>Toh, guarda che cos'ha trovato la capra...</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vaya, mirad lo que ha traído la cabra.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_DARIUS_1</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_CIV_SHORT] needs this. I thank you for your cooperation.</English>
		<French>On a besoin de ça. Immédiatement. Merci de votre coopération.</French>
		<German>Das ist unsere Forderung und wir verlangen sofortige Erfüllung! Danke für Eure Kooperation!</German>
		<Italian>Ecco cosa ci serve. Ora. Grazie per la collaborazione.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Necesitamos esto. Ahora mismo. Gracias por vuestra cooperación.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_DARIUS_1</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_CIV_SHORT] demands this. Please comply.</English>
		<French>Vous devriez nous donner ce que nous voulons, [CT_NAME], l'avenir de votre peuple en dépend</French>
		<German>Ihr solltet unsere Forderung erfüllen, [CT_NAME] - denn damit werdet Ihr über die Zukunft Eures Volkes entscheiden!</German>
		<Italian>Dovresti darci ciò che vogliamo, [CT_NAME]. Il futuro della tua gente dipende da questo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Deberíais darnos lo que queremos, [CT_NAME]: el futuro de vuestro pueblo depende de ello.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_DARIUS_1</Tag>
		<English>I, [OUR_NAME], have made a decree; let it be done with speed.</English>
		<French>Je ne crois qu'à l'argent, [CT_NAME]. Payez ou vous en subirez les conséquences.</French>
		<German>Ich stehe auf Glitzerzeug, [CT_NAME], also überlasst uns Eure Wertsachen oder tragt die Konsequenzen!</German>
		<Italian>Vado matto per i soldi, [CT_NAME]. Daccene o paga le conseguenze delle tue azioni.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Me gustan los tesoros, [CT_NAME]. Entregádnoslos o sufrid las consecuencias.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JOAO_1</Tag>
		<English>Ah. Hello. I am the lord of lords, not the server of servants. My name is [OUR_NAME]. I rule the [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. I extend my hand to you in peace.</English>
		<French>Félicitations, [CT_NAME] ! Vos explorations vous ont enfin conduit jusqu'à moi !</French>
		<German>Ich gratuliere, [CT_NAME]! Endlich haben Euch Eure Erkundungsreisen zu mir geführt!</German>
		<Italian>Congratulazioni, [CT_NAME]! Alla fine le tue esplorazioni ti hanno portato da me!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Felicidades, [CT_NAME]! ¡Por fin vuestras exploraciones os han traído hasta mí!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_JOAO_1</Tag>
		<English>Go away, you vile person!</English>
		<French>Disparaissez, scélérat !</French>
		<German>Hinfort, niederträchtige Person!</German>
		<Italian>Va' via, essere spregevole!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Largo, vil entre viles!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_JOAO_1</Tag>
		<English>Not while there are still so many [CT_CIV_ADJ] warriors to slaughter!</English>
		<French>Pas tant qu'il reste tant de guerriers [CT_CIV_ADJ:3] à massacrer !</French>
		<German>Nicht, solange es noch so viele [CT_CIV_ADJ:3] Krieger niederzumetzeln gibt!</German>
		<Italian>Non fino a quando ci saranno tanti guerrieri [CT_CIV_ADJ] da sterminare!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No mientras aún queden tantos guerreros [CT_CIV_ADJ:3] por matar!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_JOAO_1</Tag>
		<English>I greet you with effusive ebullience, my good friend.</English>
		<French>Je vous souhaite chaleureusement la bienvenue, mon bon ami.</French>
		<German>Ich grüße Euch mit Überschwang und in Freundschaft.</German>
		<Italian>Ti saluto con affettuoso entusiasmo, mio caro amico.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Os saludo con efusiva efervescencia, colega del alma.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_JOAO_1</Tag>
		<English>What now?</English>
		<French>Quoi encore ?</French>
		<German>Was wollt Ihr nun schon wieder?</German>
		<Italian>Che c'è ora?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y ahora qué?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_JOAO_1</Tag>
		<English>If it pleases you, [CT_NAME], [OUR_CIV_SHORT] could use a little assistance.</English>
		<French>Si vous n'y voyez aucun inconvénient, [CT_NAME], les [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] auraient besoin d'aide.</French>
		<German>Wenn Ihr die Güte hättet, [CT_NAME]: Das Volk von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] könnte ein wenig Unterstützung gebrauchen.</German>
		<Italian>Se ti va bene, [CT_NAME], [OUR_CIV_SHORT] avrebbe bisogno di un po' di aiuto.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Si os complace, [CT_NAME], a [OUR_CIV_SHORT] no le iría mal una ayudita.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_JOAO_1</Tag>
		<English>We could use your aid, [CT_NAME]. Can you spare us this?</English>
		<French>Nous aurions besoin de votre aide, [CT_NAME]. Pourriez-vous nous donner ceci ?</French>
		<German>Wir könnten Eure Hilfe brauchen, [CT_NAME]. Seid Ihr einverstanden?</German>
		<Italian>Ci farebbe comodo il tuo aiuto, [CT_NAME]. Puoi darci questo?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nos iría bien vuestra ayuda, [CT_NAME]. ¿Podrías darnos esto?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_JOAO_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_NAME], they do not call me the Perfect Prince for nothing. Refuse me this at your peril.</English>
		<French>[CT_NAME], je vais vous faire une offre que vous ne pourrez pas refuser.</French>
		<German>Ich mache Euch ein Angebot, das Ihr nicht ablehnen könnt, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>[CT_NAME], ti sto facendo un'offerta che non puoi rifiutare.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[CT_NAME], os voy a hacer una oferta que no podréis rechazar.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_GILGAMESH_1</Tag>
		<English>A man's life is short. Each man dies, but my immortality is sure. If my enemy strikes me most dead, it will be said: I fought. No shame! If I do my enemy strike down, then I will have greater fame. Whatever I try I shall succeed. You have fought lion and wolf, [CT_NAME] -- bring that courage with me now.</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, misérable mortel. Je suis [OUR_NAME], divin chef des [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3]. Que pouvez-vous faire pour moi ?</French>
		<German>Willkommen, sterbliches Wesen. Ich bin [OUR_NAME], gottgleiches Staatsoberhaupt des Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Was könnt Ihr für mich tun?</German>
		<Italian>Benvenuto, debole mortale. Sono [OUR_NAME], capo divino di [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Come puoi servirmi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Se os da la bienvenida, insignificante mortal. Soy [OUR_NAME], líder divino de [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. ¿En qué podéis ayudarme?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_GILGAMESH_1</Tag>
		<English>Give us dreams, O mighty God, that sharpen the steel of our resolve! Pray thus, [CT_NAME], and know that I do the same.</English>
		<French>Non ! Vos prières resteront sans réponse !</French>
		<German>Nein! Eure Gebete werden nicht erhört!</German>
		<Italian>No! Le tue preghiere non verranno ascoltate!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No! ¡Vuestros ruegos serán desoídos!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_GILGAMESH_1</Tag>
		<English>This dream is truly horrible. But with these deeds I shall ensure my everlasting memory in the minds of my sons. It is too early for peace.</English>
		<French>Cette guerre continuera jusqu'à ce que ma soif de sang soit totalement étanchée.</French>
		<German>Dieser Krieg wird so lange dauern, bis es meinen göttlichen Gaumen nicht mehr nach Blut dürstet!</German>
		<Italian>Questa guerra continuerà fino a quando la mia divina sete di sangue non si sarà calmata.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta guerra continuará hasta que mi divina sed de sangre se sacie por completo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_GILGAMESH_1</Tag>
		<English>I was dreaming: I was a wild man, so this good dream I know. O great God above, give us strength, my friend and I! Give us courage to surpass our fear of the enemy. Life is short. But standing together, two friends can prevail...</English>
		<French>Vous avez vraiment de la chance d'être une nouvelle fois en ma divine présence, [CT_NAME]. J'imagine que vous avez amené des cadeaux ?</French>
		<German>Ihr seid wahrhaft gesegnet, dass Ihr Euch erneut in meinem göttlichen Glanz sonnen dürft, [CT_NAME]. Ich nehme an, Ihr habt angemessene Geschenke dabei?</German>
		<Italian>Sei davvero fortunato a trovarti ancora una volta in presenza della mia divinità, [CT_NAME]. Presuppongo che tu abbia dei regali.</Italian>
		<Spanish>No sabéis la suerte que tenéis de poder comparecer una vez más ante mi divina presencia, [CT_NAME]. Supongo que me habréis traído ofrendas, ¿no?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_GILGAMESH_1</Tag>
		<English>I am the greatest king in this world. Fame will attend my sons for ever more. [CT_CIV_SHORT] is mocked by [OUR_CIV_SHORT], and [OUR_NAME] is proclaimed for the glory he has obtained.</English>
		<French>Parlez vite, avant que je ne vous foudroie de ma colère divine, scélérat !</French>
		<German>Redet, bevor ich die Geduld mit Euch falscher Schlange verliere!</German>
		<Italian>Parla in fretta, prima che scateni un po' di buona vecchia ira divina su di te, bugiardo!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hablad rápidamente antes de que abra un gran frasco de cólera divina y la vierta sobre vos, serpiente.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_GILGAMESH_1</Tag>
		<English>I had a dream just now, of you and me walking through a mountain pass... When down the mountain came upon our heads. Like a man's hands upon two flies. I fear this omen, and think we should make sacrifice.</English>
		<French>Même les civilisations les plus primitives peuvent détenir quelque chose susceptible de contribuer à la grandeur des [OUR_CIV_SHORT], [CT_NAME]. Par exemple :</French>
		<German>Selbst die mickrigste Kultur besitzt etwas, was sie dem großen Volk von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] überlassen kann, [CT_NAME]. Zum Beispiel das hier:</German>
		<Italian>Anche la cultura più infima può contribuire in qualche modo alla grandezza di [OUR_CIV_SHORT], [CT_NAME]. Per esempio:</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hasta la más inferior de las culturas puede contribuir en algo a la grandeza de [OUR_CIV_SHORT], [CT_NAME]. Por ejemplo:</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_GILGAMESH_1</Tag>
		<English>I had a dream just now. I lay helpless on the ground. Above a great bull bellowed in delight. Each breath on me did I feel, each stamp of hooves as the ground shook. ...And yet I was brought water to slake my thirst.</English>
		<French>Décidez-vous, [CT_NAME] : on fait affaire, oui ou non ?</French>
		<German>Entscheidet Euch, [CT_NAME]: Ja oder Nein!</German>
		<Italian>Decidi ora, [CT_NAME]: affare fatto, o no?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Decidid, [CT_NAME]: ¿hay trato o no?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_GILGAMESH_1</Tag>
		<English>I had a dream just now. Dark lightening did make bright all about. A thunder shook me from head to feet. And fire rained, and ash came after fire and covered all things. You must answer this omen with sacrifice, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Si vous souhaitez que votre pitoyable civilisation survive, je vous conseille de nous faire une modeste donation. Immédiatement.</French>
		<German>Wenn Euch am Überleben Eurer armseligen Zivilisation gelegen ist, solltet Ihr uns schleunigst Tribut zollen. Sofort!</German>
		<Italian>Se vuoi che la tua debole civiltà sopravviva, ti consiglio di farci una piccola donazione. Immediatamente.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Si queréis que vuestra insignificante civilización sobreviva, os insto a que nos hagáis un pequeño donativo. De inmediato.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BOUDICA_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME], Queen of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. The Gods are on our side in our quest for vengeance. Are you?</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, [CT_NAME] ! Les puissants [OUR_CIV_SHORT:3] veulent la paix avec votre misérable civilisation. Enfin, pour l'instant.</French>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]! Das mächtige Volk von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] wünscht friedvolle Beziehungen zu Eurer bedauernswerten Nation. Zumindest für den Augenblick ...</German>
		<Italian>Ti do il benvenuto, [CT_NAME]! [OUR_CIV_SHORT] vuole la pace con la tua piccola e debole civiltà. Per il momento, almeno.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Os doy la bienvenida, [CT_NAME]! La poderosa tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT] busca la paz con vuestra débil civilización de pacotilla. De momento, claro está.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_BOUDICA_1</Tag>
		<English>Go away before I throw you to the badgers!</English>
		<French>Disparaissez avant que je vous jette aux blaireaux !</French>
		<German>Hinfort, bevor ich Euch einkerkern lasse!</German>
		<Italian>Vattene, prima che ti getti in pasto ai tassi!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Largaos antes de que os eche a los tejones!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_BOUDICA_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_CIV_ADJ] greed spares neither the old or the virgins. We will fight you.</English>
		<French>Ne me faites pas rire !</French>
		<German>Macht Euch nicht lächerlich!</German>
		<Italian>Non farmi ridere!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡No me hagáis reír!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_BOUDICA_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]! I smell victory this day.</English>
		<French>Mes respects, [CT_NAME] ! Montons sur mon puissant char et sus aux barbares ! Mais c'est moi qui conduis !</French>
		<German>Seid gegrüßt, [CT_NAME]! Lasst uns meinen prachtvollen Streitwagen besteigen und ein paar Barbaren jagen! Ihr dürft mein "Beifahrer" sein!</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]! Monta sul mio potente cocchio e diamo insieme la caccia a qualche barbaro! Puoi stare davanti, se vuoi!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Saludos, [CT_NAME]! ¡Montemos en mi imponente carro y vayamos a cazar unos bárbaros! ¡Podréis sentaros a mi lado!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_BOUDICA_1</Tag>
		<English>When the [CT_CIV_ADJ] people realise their small force and the justice of our cause, they will know it is victory or death.</English>
		<French>Allez-y : faites-moi rire.</French>
		<German>Nur zu: Macht mich glücklich! </German>
		<Italian>Coraggio: fatti ammazzare. </Italian>
		<Spanish>Adelante, alegradme el día. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_BOUDICA_1</Tag>
		<English>[CT_CIV_ADJ] legions are cowering in their forts. Pay us tribute, and they may remain.</English>
		<French>Offririez-vous ce modeste présent à vos bons amis ?</French>
		<German>Würdet Ihr Euren Freunden ein kleines Geschenk machen?</German>
		<Italian>Hai un piccolo regalo per dei buoni amici?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿No podríais hacerles un regalito a vuestros buenos amigos?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_BOUDICA_1</Tag>
		<English>The [CT_CIV_ADJ] must pay tribute to the [OUR_EMPIRE]. This is my resolve.</English>
		<French>Donnez-nous ce que nous demandons, [CT_NAME]. Franchement, vous avez besoin de tous les amis possibles.</French>
		<German>Schlagt ein, [CT_NAME]. Ist es nicht so, dass Ihr jeden Freund braucht, den Ihr kriegen könnt?</German>
		<Italian>Dacci ciò che vogliamo, [CT_NAME]. Francamente, hai bisogno di tutti gli amici che riesci a farti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos esto, [CT_NAME]. La verdad, necesitáis todos los amigos posibles.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_BOUDICA_1</Tag>
		<English>Your armies could never stand the roar of our thousands, least of all our charge and hand-to-hand fighting. I will only ask once.</English>
		<French>Donnez-nous jusqu'à la dernière pièce de votre coffre, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Ihr solltet bereit sein, Euer Bestes zu geben, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Dacci tutto, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Aflojad la pasta, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
